Finding Aid for Dept. of Anatomy and Cell Biology (University of Michigan) Records 1902-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Anatomy and Cell Biology (University of Michigan) records 1902-1989, 1935-1982
University of Michigan. Dept. of Anatomy and Cell Biology.
2 linear feet (in 3 boxes)
Teaching and research unit of the University of Michigan Medical School. Records include correspondence, 1936-1953, of department chairman Bradley M. Patten; lists of examination questions, 1910-1921; schedules of lectures for courses, 1936-1958; information sheets on faculty members, 1932-1933; minutes of the General Committee of the Division of the Biological Sciences, 1951-1952; and grant applications and annual reports of the chairman A. Kent Christensen, 1978-1982.
87129 Bimu C26 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group came in periodic accessions (Donor nos. 2937 and 7265 ). The most recent accession came as a transfer from the 2002 donation by the Historical Center for the Health Science (Donor no. 8111).
The records are open for research except for the series Personnel Files which are closed in accord with university policy and applicable law.
When the Department of Medicine and Surgery was organized in 1849, one of the five professorships was devoted to anatomy. Moses Gunn first held this position. (See following page for listing of all department chairs.) Gunn's main interest was surgery, however, and in 1854 he convinced his friend Corydon L. Ford to come to Michigan to teach anatomy. Ford held the position until his death forty years later. Ford husbanded the department through a period of large growth. The department's facilities grew several times during his tenure. James P. McMurrich became chair in 1894 and broadened the curriculum beyond the teaching of gross anatomy to medical students. New courses were offered and some sections were opened to graduate students.
The correspondence of the next three chairs--George L. Streeter, G. Carl Huber and Bradley Patten are included in this record group. Dr. Streeter expanded the teaching staff and broadened the influence of the department. Dr. Huber similarly expanded the research of the department. Under Dr. Patten the department was separated into 3 divisions: embryology and histology, the laboratory of comparative neurology, and gross anatomy. The restructuring was put into effect to accommodate the growing number of students in various anatomy classes.
There is no material from the tenures of department chairs Russell Woodburne and Johannes Rhodin in this record group.
A. Kent Christensen became chairman in 1978 with a mandate to build up cell biology research in the department. There was concern that the Department of Anatomy "conjure[d] up visions mainly of cadavers and skeletons." In the summer of 1981, the department changed its name to the Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology. Christensen was also responsible for the renovation of several laboratories including a new Cell Biology Laboratory.
When Christensen resigned as chairman in December 1982, the department was led by two successive interim or acting chairs. In 1989, the chair was awarded to Bruce M. Carlson.
For a history of the origins of the department through the 1950s researchers should consult Donald Huelke's three-part article on the history of the Department of Anatomy in the
University of Michigan Medical Bulletin (Volume 27, January-February 1961; Volume 28, May-June, 1962; and Volume 29, May-June, 1963).
Chairs of the Department of Anatomy
1849-1854 Moses Gunn
1854-1894 Corydon L. Ford
1894-1907 James P. McMurrich
1907-1914 George L. Streeter
1914-1934 G. Carl Huber
1935-1958 Bradley M. Patten
1958-1973 Russell T. Woodburne
1973-1978 Johannes Rhodin
1978-1981 A. Kent Christensen
Chairs of the Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology
1981-1982 A. Kent Christensen
1983-1986 Sarah W. Winans (acting)
1986-1989 Allan Beaudoin (interim)
1989-1999 Bruce M Carlson
1999-2000 Michael J. Weslsh (interim)
Chairs of the Department of Cell and Developmental Biology
2000-2002 Michael J. Weslsh (interim)
2002- James Douglas Engel
Records of the Dept. of Anatomy and Cell Biology (University of Michigan) include correspondence, 1936-1953, of department chairman Bradley M. Patten; lists of examination questions, 1910-1921; schedules of lectures for courses, 1936-1958; information sheets on faculty members, 1932-1933; minutes of the General Committee of the Division of the Biological Sciences, 1951-1952; and grant applications and annual reports of the chairman A. Kent Christensen, 1978-1982. The records are divided into four series: Chairman's Files, Grants, Personnel Material, and Departmental Histories and Photographs.
Subjects:
Cartoons.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Anatomy and Cell Biology.; University of Michigan. Division of Biological Sciences.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; Patten, Bradley M. (Bradley Merrill), 1889-1971; Christensen, A. Kent.
Genre/Form:
Cartoons.; Photographs.
- Chairman's Files
  Chairman's Files is the largest series in the collection. It contains material dealing with the administration of the department. This includes correspondence, curriculum, and faculty information. Most of the material is from A. Kent Christensen's years as chairman. There is, however, scattered correspondence from his predecessors beginning in 1902. Of note is material relating to the creation of a cell biology laboratory and rationale for a departmental name change to Department of Anatomy and Cell Biology in 1981-1982.
  - American Society Of Anatomists 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Annual Report Materials 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Baker Lecture 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Cell Biology Laboratory
    - Correspondence 1977-1979 (Box 1)
    - Plans and Drawings 1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - 1907-1908 (Box 1)
    - 1909 (Box 1)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1)
    - 1912-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1934-1938 (Box 1)
    - 1939-1940 (Box 1)
    - 1941-1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944-1949 (Box 1)
    - 1950-1953 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum
    - Cell Biology 1979-1980 (Box 1)
    - Class Syllabi 1936-1958, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Examination Questions 1910-1921 (Box 1)
  - Faculty
    - Biographical Information (Elizabeth Crosby and Bradley Patten) 1970-1983 (Box 1)
    - Information Sheets on Faculty 1932-1934, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - General Committee of the Division of Biological Sciences 1951-1952 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Committee on Course Criteria 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Historical Material 1902-1980 (Box 1)
  - Medical Building Floor Plans undated (Box 1)
  - Name Change (to Anatomy and Cell Biology) 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Review, Internal 1983-1984 (Box 1)
- Grants
  Grants contains research grants given to the department. Most of these were issued by the Department of Health, Education and Welfare, a federal agency. Christensen was the principal researcher for most of the grants in this series which date from the late 1970s and early 1980s.
  - Center for Research on Learning and Teaching 1982 (Box 1)
  - Biomedical Research Support 1982 (Box 1)
  - Dept. of Health, Education and Welfare
    - Biosynthesis and Secretion of hCG by Human Trophoblast 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Hypophyseal Response to Estrogens and Progestins 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - Localization of Hormone Receptors in the Testis 1978-1982, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Mechanism of Action of Gonadotropins in the Testis 1980 (Box 1)
    - Membrane Bound Polysomes in Endocrine Cells 1980-1984 (Box 1)
    - Morphological Characteristics of Normal and Abnormal Human and Mouse Mammary Tissue 1975-1978 (Box 1)
    - Testicular Smears for Hormone Autoradiography 1979-1981 (Box 1)
- Personnel Materials (Box 2)
  (RESTRICTED)
  The Personnel Materials series contains documentation relating to promotions, tenure decisions, searches, and merit increases from 1977 to 1989. Material in this series is restricted for 30 years from the date of creation.
  - Budget
    (includes discussions on merit raises)
    - 1978-1981 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - External Review 1985 (Box 2)
    (CLOSED until July 17, 2015 )
  - Faculty Curriculum Vitae (with evaluative comment) 1978-1983, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Promotion Committee
    - 1984-1988 (Box 2)
      (CLOSED until January 1, 2019 )
    - 1989 (Box 2)
      (CLOSED until January 1, 2020 )
  - Searches
    - Chairman 1977 (Box 2)
    - Chairman 1985-1988 (Box 2)
    - Faculty 1989 (Box 2)
- Departmental Histories and Photographs
  The Department Histories and Photographs series consists of photographs (both prints and negatives) of faculty members, graduate students, staff and technicians; articles, a typescript, and a photo album detailing the history of the department, archival files and photographs (prints and negatives) used to make departmental histories, and miscellaneous related information. The original materials date from around the 1930s, but the series also includes several copies, negatives, and prints of articles and photographs dating back to the late 19th century. Most of this series was added as a result of a transfer from the 2002 accession from the Historical Center for the Health Sciences (currently reorganized as the Center for the History of Medicine).
  - Faculty Group Portraits 1945-1983 circa 1985 (Box 3)
  - Faculty Group Portrait Negatives 1970-1983, undated (Box 3)
  - Faculty Individual Portraits 1910-1983, undated (Box 3)
  - Binder of Negatives of Individual Faculty Members 1980 (Box 3)
  - Secretary and Technician Group Portrait 1976 (Box 3)
  - Graduate Student Group Portraits and Information 1966-1981, undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1976-1982, undated (Box 3)
  - Negatives and Prints of Diagrams and Illustrations 1968, 1974, undated (Box 3)
  - Archival Material for Erikson History (Including Huelke prints and negatives) 1950-1980, undated (Box 3)
    (Many images are reprints or copy negatives of images dating from the late 19th century through the 1950s)
  - Binder with Birch History Typescript and Negatives 1948, undated (Box 3)
  - Clippings and Reprinted Histories 1902-1980 (Box 3)
    (dates of original publication)
  - Historical Photo Album undated (Box 3)
- Publications
  - Unit Publications
    - Annual Reports (Box 3)
      - Annual Report, 1980/81 (Box 3)
    - Guidelines
      - In the Interest of Human Welfare, undated (Box 3)
Related Material
For information regarding anatomical donations made to the university, the researcher should consult the University of Michigan Anatomical Donations Program Records in the Bentley Library (call no. 950 Bimu 2).